<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
  <title>Debug</title>

  <section>
    <title>Trace</title>

    <para>Reference : <ulink
    url="http://newsgroups.derkeiler.com/Archive/Comp/comp.lang.rexx/2008-07/msg00079.html">comp.lang.rexx</ulink></para>

    <para>You can turn rexx tracing on by setting the RXTRACE environment
    variable to ON. This can be handy if you use external subroutines, or
    <code>::include</code> libraries. If you find yourself about to call such an
    external routine (while tracing your own code) then you can enter:</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[Call Value 'RXTRACE','ON','ENVIRONMENT']]></programlisting>

    <para>and see what the external routine does.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Debugging from command line</title>

    <para>Assuming you have visual studio and you have a Rexx command that
    creates the problem, just type</para>

    <programlisting><![CDATA[devenv /debugexe rexx <your parameter>]]></programlisting>

    <para>Hit F5 to run, and it should stop at the location of the trap.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>A particularly useful breakpoint...</title>

    <para>Reference : <ulink
    url="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?thread_name=33bd05330704090326k1b5c62a8k1e5ac52a0674ad3b%40mail.gmail.com&amp;forum_name=oorexx-devel">oorexx-devel</ulink></para>

    <para>If you're ever working on something and you get a Rexx error message,
    you can find out exactly where the failure is coming from by setting a
    breakpoint on <code>RexxActivity::raiseException()</code>in file
    <filename>interpreter\concurrency\RexxActivity.cpp</filename>. All Rexx
    error messages end up here, so once you are here, you can display the stack
    trace to find out exactly where the error is getting raised from.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>How to determine the source location</title>

    <para>Reference : <ulink
    url="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?thread_name=4B83023E.5090507%40safedatausa.com&amp;forum_name=oorexx-devel">oorexx-devel</ulink></para>

    <para>If your program crashes, you can determine which line in which file
    was executed.</para>

    <para>Go back down the stack, until you reach the
    <code>RexxActivation::run()</code> call. Expand the <code>this</code>
    variable. You are looking for the value
    <code>this-&gt;sourceObject-&gt;programName-&gt;stringData</code>, which
    should be the name of the program that is currently running.</para>

    <para>Move up to the next frame in the stack. It should be a
    RexxInstructionXXX. Expand the <code>this</code> variable until you find the
    <code>instructionLocation</code> variable. The <code>startLine</code> field
    contains the line number currently executed.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Advanced debugging</title>

    <para>Reference : <ulink
    url="http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?forum_name=oorexx-devel&amp;max_rows=25&amp;style=nested&amp;viewmonth=200906&amp;viewday=2">oorexx-devel</ulink></para>

    <para>Sometimes, you need to put a breakpoint in a DLL which is not yet
    loaded. The case described here is a DLL loaded by Java.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Without modification of source</title>

      <para>Start <productname>Java</productname> in the debugger. You'll need
      to specify the actual java executable, not whatever is in
      <filename>C:\Windows\System32\java</filename>. You do this with the
      command:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[devenv /debugexe "C:\Program Files\...\java.exe" MyClass]]></programlisting>

      <para>Once in the debugger, set a breakpoint in your dll module using the
      breakpoint menu and a fully qualified breakpoint location. For example, to
      set a breakpoint on the AttachThread() API routine in oorexx, specify the
      breakpoing as:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[{,InterpreterInstanceStubs.cpp,rexx.dll} @63
]]></programlisting>

      <para>The @63 is the source file line number. Since you qualified this
      using the rexx.dll, it will handle the breakpoint even though rexx.dll is
      dynamically loaded. Once this is loaded, then all of the symbols are
      available and normal means can be used to set break points. </para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>With modification of source</title>

      <para>This procedure is taken from <ulink
      url="&lt;http://ccollomb.free.fr/blog/?p=30&gt;">&lt;http://ccollomb.free.fr/blog/?p=30&gt;</ulink>,
      which explains different ways of how to insert statements in one's code to
      trigger the debugger.</para>

      <para>Define this macro:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[#define BREAK_HERE_SINGLESTEP() __asm __emit 0xF1]]></programlisting>

      <para>and later in the code use it wherever you want to start to debug in
      single step mode, enter:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[BREAK_HERE_SINGLESTEP();]]></programlisting>

      <para>This macro has the stated benefit, that it goes right into single
      stepping mode, without firing up the exception dialog. If, for some
      reasons, the breakpoint is not activated, then you can modify the macro to
      use one of these other ways to set a breakpoint:</para>

      <programlisting><![CDATA[__debugbreak();
DebugBreak();
_CrtDbgBreak();
__asm int 3;
__asm __emit 0xCC;
__asm __emit 0xCD; __asm __emit 0×03;]]></programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>


TODO : add this text
From Rony
While working on Linux and using gdb for debugging, there were constantly SIGSEGV errors that gdb reported and stopped execution.

Researching this problem on the net it turns out that Java may refer to inaccessible memory addresses which it will handle when SIGSEGV occur. In the case of running it under gdb such exceptions are intercepted by gdb. In order to let Java handle the SIGSEGV exceptions one needs to add the following line before starting the program that uses Java:

handle SIGSEGV nostop noprint pas
